one of the things people do with anxiety
is they try to transmute it into fear
because if they can transmute anxiety
into fear then they can do something as
opposed to just have that of ambiguity
and man that is an intense notion mm-hmm
one of the things that people do with
anxiety is they transmuted into fear Wow
and it's the in-depth and and that could
that kind of feeds into the conspiracy
generation because what conspiracies do
as psychological adaptive mechanisms is
they translate existential anxiety into
actionable fear because now there's the
threat whatever as the Cabal which which
how it works however overwhelming is at
least concrete enough that in principle
agency is possible so you know I
sometimes call this the demonization
strategy one of the ways you know it I
sometimes say to people I mean this sort
of half ironically it would be kind of
wonderful if there was a devil it would
be wonderful if all of the evil and
suffering actually had you know an
orchestrated genius behind it because
then at last we could know what it is
we're supposed to do yeah very clearly
we we've turned it from an ill-defined
problem into a well-defined problem it's
a hard problem but you know what it's
not anymore it's not an ill-defined
problem right so how do you know you're
not in the Cabal yeah how do we how do
we go about as individuals navigate
these child never getting these choppy
waters well I'm wondering if that's I'm
wondering if that's one of the things I
mean so a few minutes ago you were
talking about a kind of wisdom we need
in order to write sure we're going down
the left-hand as you as you put it I'm
suggesting to you that part of that
wisdom might be the kind of self
knowledge of this modal kind of self
deception and one of the so if I'm aware
that I'm doing a lot of shifting of
anxiety into fear that for me is a red
flag that forget what flag I love it
right
a red flag that I'm probably getting
into conspiratorial Kabbalistic gnostic
in the pejorative sense of the word kind
of thinking right yes absolutely it's
really interesting I'm loving the the
inverse where the Black Plague broke the
religion that was a religion yep and
this this new thing is is what gives
rise to the religion that's not a
religion you just you just described one
you know one piece one one wouldn't you
is it a kailash homily no a reading
right a reading a reading from the book
of the religion it's not a religion
chemistry if you notice that you're
shifting anxiety into fear then it's a
red flag yeah that's a red flag and then
the converse would be not just teaching
people amelioration of anxiety that's a
good you need something more like what
we saw happen after the Black Plague
where we you again the the
identification of your interior life
it's fun the grammar of that is
fundamentally changed it would have to
be something more like in that there are
more deep so deeper into the guts of the
psyche the response to uncertainty and
dynamic change is something other than
anxiety and we all but it has to be well
no no we've reconfigured the grammar
before we have done this multiple times
so so one is you know first of all
perhaps a first step is while am i
translating anxiety into fear right well
that's bad but another one is can I get
deeper than the response of anxiety and
come up with something other than
anxiety as a response to uncertainty oh
it's so good isn't it I mean it's funny
like this it's like it's like going
through the looking glass because we
were talking about his faith a kind of
faith yes if aid from the we had talked
about we've talked about the several
times we've come to be the same place
many times right yeah it's not an
ideological it's not an irrational
commitment to an ideology it's not a
willful assertion of a proposition
it's a cultivated sense of being uh like
having a participatory conformity with
an ongoing transformative process and
it's continuity of contact rather than
closure into conclusion right boys
that's a bunch of good words man so
timestamp whatever this is right now
that was good that was it
somebody write that down in the comments
yeah the the visual image I have is of
like a buoy in the ocean that has you
know it just it's weighted such that
even as the water I was having a sailing
imagery the person who can sort of can
ride the edge of the storm a family
right yeah it's you don't want to get
swamped right that's the key yeah and so
you know having a series of capacities
and abilities including the ability to
just sort of like surrender to what's
happening so that you're you're not
breaking as the system pushes on you but
you're actually able to just keep that
at all always stay in continuity of
contact yeah always stay there because
you know that if you're out of there
you're in trouble
and if you're in there you can at least
recover all right depending if the wave
if the winds died down a little bit
you're back into assailant yep yeah
that's that's the key yeah that's cool
that's really cool there's a story by
Joseph Conrad about a ship that gets
swamped and that sailors are all stant
are sort of holding onto the side of the
ship it's actually been swamped and and
Alliston the captain he's just they're
all watching him good news they have a
they have a kind of they have a faith in
him but he's watching and he's watching
and he's watching and then all of a
sudden goes okay now raise that sail
that sail that sail and then he goes
right timing of wind and wave and the
shipwrights there you go so he like he's
he represents exactly that buoy right he
was young he was aware that he even
being swamped is not being swamped yes
yes yeah all in all it seemed like all
was lost but as long as the captain has
got their eye on the wind you know that
you have a chance and they knew long as
he had his eye on the winds that they
had a chance and so they stayed together
in pop and that's that's it man it's a
great story yeah hmm yeah so that's it's
funny because so he didn't do is he
didn't lose faith he didn't he didn't he
didn't fall into learned helplessness or
neuroses and he stated he wasn't just
doing willful assertion he's not a Rambo
hero right yes the point he's not a
Rambo hero and he doesn't just oh I will
you know he doesn't just sort of muscle
or force his way through it's it's like
the whoo way of taoism right he he fine
he looks for the grain and he have
sensitivity to find the grain and align
himself with it so that he gets that
timing and it's just like that yeah